{"tossups": [{"question": "<b>Cecil Andrus declared a state of emergency in response to this event and authorized the use of facilities at Bonners Ferry. Lon Horiuchi was charged with manslaughter for his actions during this event. Martin Fackler claimed that (+) Art Roderick killed a dog in the prelude to this event, which also resulted in the death of William Degan. (*) </b> Kevin Harris was awarded $380,000 in damages for injuries sustained during this event despite the fact he had killed a US Marshall. For the points, name this 1992 siege of Randy Weaver and his family in northern Idaho.", "answer": "<b> Ruby Ridge</b> standoff (or siege, etc.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Arnold Deutsch was known as \u201cOtto\u201d when he served as the first controller of this group; that role was later assumed by Bob Stewart, who worked a transmitter in Wimbledon.</b> <b>Andrew Boyle\u2019s</b><em><b> The Climate of Treason</b></em><b> announced Anthony (+)</b> <b>Blunt\u2019s membership in</b> <b>this group, which was discovered by the Venona Project. The names \u201cHicks,\u201d \u201cLiszt,\u201d and\u201cTony\u201d were used by members of this group, which included (*)</b> Kim Philby and Guy Burgess. For the points, name this group of British spies who reported to the Soviets in the 1940s and early 50s.", "answer": "<b> Cambridge Five</b> (accept<b> Cambridge Four</b>; accept<b> Cambridge</b> Spy<b> Ring</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s mistress, Domitila de Castro, once found him weeping after this man claimed he saw a ghost of his wife. During a rebellion against this leader led by Frei Caneca, rebels drank (+) aguardiente instead of wine. The Confederation of the Equator formed to oppose this man, whose forces fought the Cisplatine War over what is now Uruguay. This man, one of many nicknamed (*)</b> \u201cThe Liberator,\u201d was a son of John IV of Portugal; after he declared independence, he was crowned at the Old Cathedral of Rio de Janiero. For the points, name this first ruler of the Brazilian Empire.", "answer": "Dom<b> Pedro I</b> (accept<b> Pedro IV of Portugal</b>; prompt on \u201cPedro\u201d alone)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>E.P. Thompson argued in a 1967 article partially named for this concept that modern conceptions of time arose from its associated work-discipline. Another work partially titled</b> <b>for this concept argues that it arose from the unprovable nature of (+)</b> <b>predestination;</b> <b>that work calls this concept an \u201ciron cage\u201d and notes that Catholic countries had fewer merchants than Protestant ones. The most famous critic of this system claimed it exists when (*)</b> labor is separated from the means of production. For the points, name this economic system whose<em> Spirit</em> was studied with the<em> Protestant Ethic</em> by Max Weber [vay-ber] and which was critiqued by Karl Marx.", "answer": "<b> capitalism</b> (accept Time, Work-Discipline, and Industrial<b> Capitalism</b>; accept the Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of <b>Capitalism</b> after \u201cunprovable\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {"question": "<b>During this event, Paraska Korolyuk became a folk hero for camping out in support of protesters. The start date of this event was declared as its country\u2019s \u201cDay of Freedom.\u201d</b> <b>Participants in this event often waved flags with the word (+)</b> <b>\u201ctak,\u201d which translates</b> <b>to \u201cyes.\u201d Protests congregated in the Maidan Nezalezhnosti [nez-ah-lezh-no-stee], or Independence Square, during this event, whose target was supported by the incumbent (*) </b>Leonid Kuchma. Fraudulent elections that led to Viktor Yanukovych\u2019s victory in an election sparked, for the points, what revolution that brought Viktor Yushchenko to power in Ukraine?", "answer": "<b> Orange Revolution</b> (\u201dRevolution\u201d not needed after mentioned; accept<b> 2004 and/or 2005 Ukrainian Revolution</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>The name of this policy apparently derived from a fable by Aesop that the Lady Kennet once shared with another nation\u2019s diplomat. \u201cFlexible reciprocity\u201d formed the basis for (+) aid provisions using this policy. It was tarnished after the revelation that one side possibly bribed another to attend a landmark 2000 summit. The adoption of this policy led to the joint operation of the Mount (*) </b> Gumgang Tourist Region and the Kaesong Industrial Park. Kim Dae-jung advocated for, for the points, what South Korean policy that softened relations with the North?", "answer": "<b> Sunshine</b> Policy (accept Taebuk<b> hwahae hyomnyok chongch\u2019aek</b>; accept<b> Reconciliation and Cooperation</b> Policy with the North; prompt on descriptive answers of South Korea softening relations with North Korea before \u201cSouth Korea\u201d is read) (7) <b>During this king\u2019s reign, Simon Metcalfe issued a trading call, then used cannons to</b> <b>During this king\u2019s reign, Simon Metcalfe issued a trading call, then used cannons to</b> <b>massacre the citizens of Olowalu; Metcalfe\u2019s assistants, John Young and (+)</b> <b>massacre the citizens of Olowalu; Metcalfe\u2019s assistants, John Young and (+)</b> <b>Isaac Davis,</b> <b>then helped this king unify his kingdom. This king fought alongside his uncle in the skirmish that killed James Cook, after which he was awarded the protectorate over his country\u2019s war god (*)</b> Ku. After being attacked by fishermen during a war, this king promoted the safety of civilians in the Law of the Splintered Paddle. For the points, name this king, the founder of unified Hawaii. ANSWER:<b> Kamehameha</b> I (or<b> Kamehameha</b> the Great)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Jim Kennally planned to steal this object and ransom it for $200,000, but was caught in a sting operation by Lewis Swegles. Fleetwood Lindley was the last living person to see this object, which he described as wearing (+) mildewed clothes. John Power created a \u201cGuard of Honor\u201d to protect this object, which he hid in a muddy basement for over 20 years before it was protected under concrete. This object embarked on a national tour that started in the (*)</b> East Room of the White House and ended in Oak Ridge Cemetery in 1865. For the points, name this object that was interred in a Springfield, Illinois tomb.", "answer": "the<b> corpse</b> of Abraham<b> Lincoln</b> (accept equivalents, like<b> Lincoln\u2019s body</b>,<b> Lincoln\u2019s remains</b>, etc.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This event is the subject of the 2006 documentary</b><em><b> Freedom\u2019s Fury</b></em><b>, narrated by Mark Spitz, who was coached by a central figure of it. This event was stopped with a minute left</b> <b>to play, and its declared winner then defeated (+)</b> <b>Yugoslavia 2-1 to win the gold medal.</b> <b>Yugoslavia 2-1 to win the gold medal.</b> <b>An iconic photo from this event shows Ervin Zador in with a massive cut near his (*)</b> <b>An iconic photo from this event shows Ervin Zador in with a massive cut near his (*)</b> eye which was caused by a punch in the face by Valentin Prokopov. For the points, name this Olympic contest between two countries involved in a 1956 revolution in Budapest.", "answer": "<b> Blood in the Water</b> Match (accept descriptions of the<b> water polo</b> match between<b> USSR and Hungary</b> at the 1956 Melbourne Olympics; accept<b> Soviet Union</b> or<b> Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</b>, etc. in place of USSR; prompt on partial answers; do not accept Russia in place of USSR)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A captain working for this state\u2019s army abuses an orderly by beating him on the legs during nighttime work sessions that he schedules to separate the orderly from the woman</b> <b>he loves. This state is symbolized by the Bulgars, who are at war with the (+)</b> <b>Avars in</b> <em><b>Candide</b></em><b>. An officer from this state titles a D.H. Lawrence short story; in another story, Elisabeth (*) </b> Rousset sleeps with an officer from this state\u2019s army in the story \u201cBall of Fat.\u201d For the points, name this state whose 1870 war with France provides the backdrop of many Guy de Maupassant stories.", "answer": "<b> Prussia</b> (accept The<b> Prussia</b>n Officer; accept Franco-<b>Prussia</b>n War)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "<b>One ruler of this city drowned in the Gargliano River after a battle of the same name. One ruler of this city was once married to Eleanor of Toledo and members of the (+) Strozzi and Albizzi families aligned against another ruler of this city. A ruler of this city was given the nickname the \u201cUnfortunate\u201d while another survived a 1478 assassination attempt at a High Mass in this city\u2019s main cathedral. That event in this city was the (*)</b> Pazzi Conspiracy. Sandro Botticelli was patronized by a leader of this city known as Lorenzo the Magnificent. For the points, name this Italian city ruled by the Medici family.", "answer": "<b> Florence</b> (accept<b> Firenze</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Italian photographer Daniele Volpe\u2019s book</b><em><b> Chukel</b></em><b> documents the effects of a genocide in this country. In 2013, a former leader of this country who implemented the (+) \u201cGuns or Beans\u201d policy was charged with killing 1,771 members of the Ixil [eeks-eel] people. The film </b><em><b>When the Mountains Tremble</b></em><b> is set in this country, where the URNG guerrilla movement fought a decades-long civil war. Nobel Peace Prize winner Rigoberta (*) </b> Menchu protested atrocities that were carried out against the indigenous Mayan peoples of, for the points, what Central American country once led by Efrain Rios Montt?", "answer": "<b> Guatemala</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This resource is the subject of the Falkenmark indicator. Patricia de Lille recently faced a vote of no confidence in the midst of protests regarding this resource. In the wake of the</b> <b>2016 Uri attacks, (+)</b> <b>India threatened to unilaterally repeal a 1960 treaty governing this</b> <b>resource. The Strategic Foresight Group released a 2011 report rethinking this resource in the Middle East titled</b><em><b> The Blue Peace</b></em><b>. (*) </b> Cape Town recently indefinitely postponed its \u201cDay Zero\u201d for, for the points, what resource, thus angering many farmers who had released their remaining reserves?", "answer": "fresh<b> water</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A Native American named Little Thomas led a revolt in this territory that resulted in</b> <b>the scalping of its governor Charles Dent. Before leaving for Alta California, (+)</b> <b>Stephen</b> <b>Kearney set up a namesake legal code for this territory. In 1862, John Slough defeated Charles Pyron at the Glorieta Pass in the (*)</b> Sangre de Christo Mountains in this territory, which existed from 1850 to 1912. This territory was governed from a city that would become the oldest state capital in the US. For the points, name this state whose territorial capital was Santa Fe.", "answer": "<b> New Mexico</b> Territory", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The artist of this work, which was inspired by an illustration in</b><em><b> Harper\u2019s Weekly</b></em><b>,</b> <b>claimed that (+)</b> <b>\u201cFew Eastern people appreciate the sky-rocket bounds\u201d of the title</b> <b>\u201cFew Eastern people appreciate the sky-rocket bounds\u201d of the title</b> <b>character. This work, which was given as a gift to (*)</b> <b>character. This work, which was given as a gift to (*)</b> Teddy Roosevelt, depicts a man who is holding a quirt while grabbing the manes of a wild horse. For the points, name this Frederic Remington sculpture of a cowboy.", "answer": "<b> Bronco Buster</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A state park adjoining this body of water is named for singer Sonny Bono, who served as a Republican congressman for an adjoining district. The former resort town of Bombay Beach lies on this body of water, as does a community that has been touted as a model</b> <b>for (+)</b> <b>anarchist societies, Slab City. This body of water, which is fed by the Alamo and</b> <b>anarchist societies, Slab City. This body of water, which is fed by the Alamo and</b> <b>San Gorgonio Rivers, suffers from (*)</b> <b>San Gorgonio Rivers, suffers from (*)</b> frequent fish die-offs and a pervasively bad smell that has ruined its tourism industry. A 1905 mishap on the Imperial Canal accidentally created, for the points, what artificial inland sea in Southern California?", "answer": "<b> Salton</b> Sea", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>Participants in these events drank a mixture of mint and barley possibly infused with alcohol and ergot. In the 2nd century BC, the Eumolpidae [you-mole-pid-ay] and the (+) Kerykes [care-ih-keez] families managed these events and opened their availability to most non-barbarians in Greece. Clement of Alexandria recorded a password used by people in these events, where (*) </b> priestesses acted out the teaching of agriculture to Triptolemus and the abduction of Persephone by Hades. For the points, name this secretive Greek cult based around the worship of Demeter.", "answer": "<b> Eleusinsian Mysteries</b> [ell-oo-sin-ee-in] (prompt on Cult of Demeter or Cult of Persephone before read)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b>During this war, the U.S. president said \u201cWe are ready to plead at the bar of history\u201din a Flag Day Address. Daylight Savings Time and Time Zones were first implemented by</b> <b>the U.S. government during this war, in which the (+)</b> <b>Lever Act established controls on</b> <b>fuel distribution. Bernard Baruch ran the War Industries Board during this war, during which (*)</b> Herbert Hoover supervised price controls on wheat. For the points, the U.S. entered what war after German attacks on merchant vessels in the Atlantic triggered a declaration from Woodrow Wilson?", "answer": "<b> World War I</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The eighth statement in a document produced at this meeting called for the enforcement</b> <b>of the Cairo Declaration. This meeting resulted in the partition of Vietnam near (+)</b> <b>Da</b> <b>Nang. At this conference, a border was shifted to decrease the size of one country by a fourth; that new border was the (*)</b> Oder-Niesse Line. Clement Attlee arrived midway through this event, at which Japan was threatened with \u201cprompt and utter destruction\u201d if it failed to surrender. For the points, name this 1945 conference held in a German city.", "answer": "<b> Potsdam</b> Conference (accept<b> Berlin Conference of the Three Heads of Government </b>of the USSR, USA and UK; accept<b> Potsdam</b> Declaration)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>James Negley\u2019s forces were able to participate in this battle because Thomas Hindman\u2019s delayed attack at McLemore\u2019s Cove allowed them to withdraw from an earlier battle. The losing side of this battle hastily retreated across the Rossville and McFarland Gaps, leaving John (+) Brannan\u2019s army trapped at Snodgrass Hill. During this battle, one side\u2019s defense was breached when Thomas Wood obeyed an erroneous command to march north. James Longstreet arrived to lead the main assault, but was unable to dislodge the (*)</b> \u201cRock\u201d of this battle, George H. Thomas. For the points, name this 1863 defeat for Union General William Rosecrans that resulted in the later Chattanooga Campaign.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Chickamauga</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A man of this name took Musasir, which compelled King Rusa to commit suicide. The conquests of a man of this name led to the legend of the Lost Ten Tribes. Marduk-Baladan</b> <b>lost Babylon to a ruler of this name, whose son (+)</b> <b>Sennacherib married Naq\u2019ia. Legend</b> <b>says a man of this name was supposed to be killed by Lugal-zage-si of Uruk; that ruler of this name was legendarily abandoned in a basket on a river and served as the (*)</b> cup-bearer to Ur-Zababa of Kish. An Assyrian ruler of this name took power from Shalmaneser V and was the son of Tiglath-Pileser III. For the points, give this name shared by a great king of Akkad.", "answer": "<b> Sargon</b> (accept<b> Sargon the Great</b> or<b> Sargon II</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A Communist leader during this event names a square where the headquarters of the French Communist Party is located. The Second Division Blind\u00b4ee disobeyed direct orders to participate in this event. One side in this event made its headquarters in the Hotel (+) Lutetia. This event started after the execution of 33 resistance members by the Gestapo in the Bois de Boulougne. During this event, Dietrich von (*) </b> Cholitz was ordered to cause mass destruction, but disobeyed and surrendered to General Leclerc instead. The French Forces of the Interior led, for the points, what event that involved tanks battling on the Champs-Elys\u00b4ees in August 1944?", "answer": "<b> Liberation of Paris</b> (accept descriptive answers relating to the<b> Nazis surrendering Paris</b>; prompt on partial answers, like \u201cBattle of Paris\u201d or \u201cNazi surrender\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>One instance of fighting in this war centered on Dhauli Hill. Pliny the Elder claims that the losing side in this conflict employed 700 war elephants under leaders like Raja Anantha.</b> <b>According to one historian, this war changed its winner\u2019s (+)</b> <b>heart from being one of</b> <b>heart from being one of</b> <b>\u201cwanton cruelty\u201d to one of \u201can exemplary piety,\u201d because this war\u2019s (*)</b> <b>\u201cwanton cruelty\u201d to one of \u201can exemplary piety,\u201d because this war\u2019s (*)</b> bloodshed inspired its winner \u201ctowards the Dharma,\u201d according to a Rock Edict. For the points, name this 3rd century BC war, a victory for the Mauryans that inspired Ashoka to convert to Buddhism.", "answer": "<b> Kalinga</b> War", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A museum in the city of Choibalsan is named after this man in honor of his service at a battle at which the Japanese Sixth Army was decisively defeated. This victor at the Battle</b> <b>of (+)</b> <b>Khalkhin Gol personally led the force that arrested Lavrentiy Beria, former head</b> <b>of the NKVD. This man\u2019s order No. 3 ordered a counter-invasion of the Suwalki region of (*) </b> Poland in response to the announcement of Operation Barbarossa in June 1941. This man called on his troops to \u201cexact a brutal revenge\u201d at the Battle of Berlin. For the points, name this Red Army commander during World War II.", "answer": "Georgy<b> Zhukov</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One work of art in this city names the town of Talamone, which this city purchased to serve as its port. One library in this city, decorated with scenes from the life of Pope Pius II, is located in a cathedral in this city which contains a mosaic floor. One work of art in this city that houses the (+) Piccolomini Library depicts Justice tied up at the seat of the throne of a devil. Ambroglio Lorenzetti\u2019s</b><em><b> Allegory of Good and Bad Government</b></em><b> is located in its city hall, which also houses (*) </b> Duccio\u2019s Maest\u00b4a. For the points, name this city, who along with its rival Florence was a center of Renaissance art.", "answer": "<b> Siena</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}], "bonuses": []}